<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Mr. Fisher the Iesuite, his fiue propositions concerning Luther. By Mr. Rogers, that worthy Oxford diuine. VVith some passages also of the said Mr. Rogers with the said Mr. Fisher. Hereunto is annexed Mr. VV.C. his dialogue of the said argument, wherein is discouered Fishers folly</title>
            <author>Rogers, Henry, ca. 1585-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116093</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1152:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Mr. Fisher the Iesuite, his fiue propositions concerning Luther. By Mr. Rogers, that worthy Oxford diuine. VVith some passages also of the said Mr. Rogers with the said Mr. Fisher. Hereunto is annexed Mr. VV.C. his dialogue of the said argument, wherein is discouered Fishers folly</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Henry, ca. 1585-1658.</author>
                  <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"A dialogue concerning this question, VVhere was your church before Luther and Caluin" by William Crashaw has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fisher, John, 1569-1641 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AN ANSWER TO M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> FISHER THE IESVITE, HIS FIVE PROPOSITIONS CONCERNING <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THER.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROGERS, that wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Oxford Diuine.</p>
                  <p>VVith ſome paſſages alſo of the said M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Rogers</hi> with the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereunto is annexed M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>VV. C.</hi> his Dialogue of the ſaid Argument, wherein is diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>d FISHERS FOLLY.</p>
                  <p>Printed M.DC.XXIII.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16581:2"/>
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> FISHER THE IESVITE, HIS FIVE PROPOSITIONS CONCERNING
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Names.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> THere is one, and but one true infallible faith,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. Heb. 11.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which none can pleaſe God: nor conſequently attaine eternall ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10. Eph. 4.</note> This infallible faith cannot be had (according to the ordinarie courſe of Gods prouidence) but by hearing Preachers and Paſtors of the true viſible Church, who onely are lawfully ſent and authorized to teach the true word of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> As therefore this one infallible faith hath beene,<note place="margin">Oſe. 2. Iſa. 56. Mat. 18. Eph. 4.</note> and muſt be in all ages: ſo there muſt be in all ages Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Paſtors of the true viſible Church, of whom all ſorts of people haue in times past (as appeareth by hiſtories) learned, and muſt in all future times learne the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible faith.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Hence it followeth, that if Proteſtants be the true
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16581:3"/>
viſible Church of God, then all ſorts of men who in euery age haue had the aforeſaid infallible faith, haue learned it by hearing Proteſtant Preachers, whoſe names may be found: who in euery former age did teach and conuert people of ſeuerall Nations vnto the faith of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Hence further it followeth, that if there cannot (as there cannot) be found in Hiſtorie the names of Proteſtant Preachers, who in all ages did teach all ſorts of faithfull people, and who conuertd ſeuerall Nations vnto the Chriſtian faith; hence it followeth I ſay, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are not the true viſible Church of Chriſt, neither are their Preachers lawfully ſent or ſufficiently authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to teach, nor the people ſecurely warranted to learne of them that one infallible faith, without which none can pleaſe God, nor if they ſo liue and die can be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Names.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any Proteſtant will anſwer the premiſes, let him ſet downe the <hi>Names of Proteſtant Preachers</hi> in all ages, who taught the people <hi>Proteſtant Doctrine</hi> in euery ſeuerall age: or elſe confeſſe that there were no ſuch before <hi>Luther:</hi> or at leaſt not in all ages to be found in Hiſtorie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHriſtian Reader,</hi> There came to my hands by the good prouidence of God this ſmall Treatiſe, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a conference betwixt one <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Rogers an Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Diuine, and one <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> a Ieſuite: as it ſhould ſeeme it was ſent incloſed to a Gentleman of good worth and worſhip one this ſide the Seas, hauing read it ouer, and perceiuing it to be of very neceſſary vſe for my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men of England, (whoſe good I deſire from my heart) I haue aduentured to publiſh it to the view of the world: the rather, becauſe therein is notably laid open and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, the weake grounds of the fiue propoſitions of <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> the Ieſuite, who is as I heare, ſo much admired of Engliſh papiſts; the which <hi>Fiſher, Sweet, Brierly, Clerk,</hi> with others of that company, doe ſtudie and ſtriue with all might and maine by divulging their written papers, as alſo their Printed Bookes full of lyes and vntruths: nay I ſay, Bookes full of blaſphemie againſt the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God of heauen, as namely that Booke Intituled. <hi>The vncaſing of Hereſie,</hi> written by <hi>O. A:</hi> and all to make proſelites of their owne faction, to ruine that flouriſhing Church and Common-wealth. I beſeech the great God of heauen, to raiſe vp dayly worthy Diuines more and more to defend his owne cauſe, againſt the Kingdome of Antichriſt, and wicked inſtruments, being very dangerous perſons both againſt Church and Common wealth. Read it with the
<pb facs="tcp:16581:4"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ioyned, &amp; ſo by Gods bleſsing thou ſhalt reape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fit by it, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue all glory to God aboue, who in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſſe things that are amiſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16581:4"/>
                  <head>THE ANSWER TO THE MASSE-PRIESTS DEMANDS, CONCERNING 1. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> and 2. <hi>Names.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Rogers.</head>
                     <p>THe three firſt poſitions I admit.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. that there is one faith.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That the ordinarie propagation of this faith is by Paſtors lawfully called.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That there haue been, and muſt be in all agee ſuch Paſtors ſo called.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. I would gladly know what they meane by thoſe wordes, <hi>[If the Proteſtants be the true viſible Church]</hi> whether ſo, as if we alone (who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Proteſtants) were of the Church, and no others? we leaue ſuch incloſing of commons to the Romaniſts, we challenge it not.</p>
                     <p>We are a true Church, not the true Church; we are a part, not the whole: we include our ſelues, we exclude not others: whether Grecians, Armenians, Aethiopians, Spaniards, or Italians, &amp;c: yet ſo they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16581:5"/>
deny no fundamentall part of the faith, either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or by conſequent.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. In the firſt, I deſire to know whether they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire we ſhould ſhew the <hi>Names</hi> of Proteſtants in Hiſtories, or their faith; this we will ſhew, that we neede not: for the name of Proteſtants is but arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie and accidentall from a proteſtation made in Germanie; and from the like accidents we may call the Romaniſts Proteſtants, for many proteſtations made in the Councell of Trent, Regiſtred in their publike Acts.</p>
                     <p>But if it be really meant thus; let the Proteſtants ſhew that their now faith was taught by lawfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in all ages: I doe (with Gods helpe) vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it, and require the ſame from the Authors of theſe propoſitions and demaunds.</p>
                     <p>This will I proue by three Argument.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>A Cauſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>A Signis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Ab Exemplis.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Which is the onely ſatisfaction here demanded: but I muſt deſire the authors not to affect obſcuritie, or to alter their words, which may alter their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as in the fiue propoſitions they haue with the multitude of needleſſe words obſcured the matter: the fourth being briefely and plainly this.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>If the Protestants be a true Church, their faith hath beene taught in all ages by lawfull Paſtors.</hi> This I grant alſo.</p>
                     <p>The ſumme of the fift is briefely this.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>If the</hi> Names <hi>of Proteſtant Paſtors in all ages can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewed, then the Proteſtants are not a true Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16581:5"/>This I denie to be of vndoubted conſequence, for the Argument negatiuely from authoritie is of no force.</p>
                     <p>In your Demands, you require the Names of ſuch as taught the Proteſtants Doctrines in all ages: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all your propoſitions before were of faith, as if all Doctrines were points of faith.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <head>Now Sit my Arguments.</head>
                           <item n="1">
                              <p>1. The faith contained in Scriptures hath beene taught in all ages.</p>
                              <p>But the faith of the Proteſtants is contained in Scriptures: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>The faith of the Proteſtants hath beene taught in all ages.</p>
                           </item>
                           <item n="2">
                              <p>2. That faith which hath the teſtimonie of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, vniuerſalitie, and conſent, was taught in all ages by lawfull Paſtors.</p>
                              <p>The faith of the Proteſtants hath theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>The faith of the Proteſtants was taught in all ages.</p>
                           </item>
                           <item n="3">
                              <p>3. That faith which hath beene taught by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors viſible in all ages, is the true faith.</p>
                              <p>But the Proteſtant faith hath beene ſo maintained by ſuch Authors: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>The Proteſtant faith hath been maintained in all ages.</p>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16581:6"/>
                     <head>The Names of ſuch as profeſsed the faith of the Proteſtants in all ages, ſince the incarnation of Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>In euery centure of yeares, which is called <hi>ſacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> an age: I will name ſome writers whoſe workes are extant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab anno 1. ad 100.</note>In the firſt centure Chriſt himſelfe, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and Euangeliſts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab 100 ad 100.</note>In the ſecond age Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, who died either <hi>Anno</hi> 100, or 101: to him we adde <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who though they liued in part of the firſt age, and part of the ſecond age, they are alwayes reckoned Fathers of that age in which they dyed: to theſe I adde <hi>Iuſtin Martyr, Iraenaeus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>. ad 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0</note>
                        <hi>Tertullian, Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen, Cyprian, Lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>antius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab 300. ad 400</note>
                        <hi>Athanaſius, Cyrillus Hieroſolymitanus, Ambroſius, Gregorius Myſtenus, Hieronymus, Ruffinus, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab 400. ad 500.</note>
                        <hi>Auguſtinus, Cyrillus Alexandrinus, Theodoretus, Vincentius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>riuenſis, Socrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Zozomen, Chryſologus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab 500. ad 600</note>
                        <hi>Bulgentius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>grius, Gregorius primus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ab 70<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>00</note>
                        <hi>Beda, Damaſcenus, Alcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Thus hauing gon halfe the way, I conclude with this Argument.</head>
                     <p>The Proteſtants ſaith is plainely expreſſed in the Canonicall Scripture, and compriſed in the Apoſtles Creede.</p>
                     <p>All theſe Fathers did profeſſe that faith which is contained in the holy Canonicall Scripture, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16581:6"/>
compriſed in the Apoſtles Creede: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All theſe did profeſſe the Proteſtants faith.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>As I admoniſhed <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fiſher</hi> to diſtinguiſh betweene Affirmation and Negation, ſo I do theſe men: and that faith is Affirmation, not Negation, for no man beleeueth which he denieth. Secondly in point of faith I like <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fe.</hi> rule.</head>
                     <p>They that are in the affirmatiue, muſt proue now all that we affirme: they affirme, as one God, three Perſons,  all the Creede; ſo that we neede not proue what our aduerſaries doe confeſſe.</p>
                     <p>But in thoſe points in variance betweene vs, they are to proue; becauſe they are affirmatiue, we nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: as vnwritten Traditions, Latin Seruice, inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>The Proteſtants faith being that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures, receiued fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vndoubtedly Canonicall in the firſt 400. yeares, which is ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily compriſed in the Apoſtles Creede, is receiued by all the Orthodox Fathers.</p>
                     <p>But thoſe Fathers aboue named be all Orthodox:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is manifeſt: the <hi>Minor</hi> I will proue out of their owne Authors, concerning all ſauing <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in whom I muſt diſtinguiſh the times: for firſt he was Orthodox, though after an Heretike.</p>
                     <p>Hauing gone thus far at this time, I vndertake for the reſt: and do require the like from the Romaniſts, viz.</p>
                     <p>That they will ſhew me the Names of ſuch as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16581:7"/>
taught the now ſaith of the Church of Rome in all ages, and let them ſet me down the Names, as I haue done.</p>
                     <p>And for inſtances in points of Romane faith in all ages, I require theſe men to ſhew me the Names of thoſe who in the 1. 2. 3. centure of yeares did preach or profeſſe vnwritten traditions to be the rule of faith: 2, that the vulgar tranſlation is authenticall: 3, that there are 7 Sacraments properly ſo called, and no more: 4, that the Bookes of the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes are Canonicall: 5, tranſubſtantiation: 6, Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints: 7, worſhipping of Images, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>This rule is propoſed by them, which though it be no neceſſarie conſequence of faith, yet it bindeth them that propoſe it to make good in particular: out of their owne poſition thus I argue.</p>
                     <p>That is the true Church whoſe faith hath had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible profeſſors in all ages.</p>
                     <p>The Romiſh faith had not viſible profeſſors in all ages: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Romane Church is not a true Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>An other Argument.</head>
                     <p>The true faith hath the teſtimonies of Vniueſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Antiquitie, and Conſent.</p>
                     <p>But the Romiſh faith (as farre as they differ from the Proteſtant faith, which they do in all the points aboue alledged) hath not teſtimonies of
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Vniuerſalitie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Antiquitie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>And Conſent.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16581:7"/>
                        <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Romiſh faith is not a true faith.</p>
                     <p>Let the Romaniſts anſwer theſe two Arguments in thoſe particular points aboue written, and I will be of their Church.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="admonition">
                  <head>An Admonition to the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do not ſo meane that thoſe Fathers by me named haue expreſsely ſet downe euery point of our faith in their ſeuerall writings, neither can the Church of Rome doe it for theirs.</p>
                  <p>But being Orthodox right beleeuing Fathers, they did conſequently maintaine the Scriptures, &amp; Apoſtles Creede.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="passages">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16581:8"/>
                  <head>Some paſſages had between Maſter <hi>Rogers,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Ieſuite, as followeth.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fiſher.</speaker>
                     <p>It being granted that there muſt be a viſible Church in all ages, <hi>of which all ſorts muſt learne faith neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to ſaluation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogers.</speaker>
                     <p>The perpetuall viſibilitie of the Church I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; But I pray you ſet me downe what a viſible Church is, and what you meane by thoſe wordes which you put of another letter, who you meane by all ſorts? whether the Children who die before they come to yeares of diſcretion doe learne this faith: or dying before they come to learne it, be not after Baptiſme parts of the viſible Church.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, What you meane by learne? whether an actuall explicite knowledge, or an habituall only implicite knowledge?</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, What points of faith you hold neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſaluation?</p>
                     <p>The queſtion propounded by <hi>M. Fiſher</hi> at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of a Gentleman who deſired ſatiſfaction, was:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fiſher.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether the Proteſtant Church was viſible in all ages, eſpecially in the ages before Luther: and whether the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16581:8"/>
names of the profeſſors thereof may be ſhewed in all ages out of good Authors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogers.</speaker>
                     <p>A Church profeſſing the ſame faith which the Proteſtants now doth, was viſible in all ages: and I doe vndertake to proue it out of good Authors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fiſher.</speaker>
                     <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fiſher <hi>vndertooke to defend the negatiue part, ſo as it did belong to his aduerſaries to proue the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>M. Fiſher</hi> explicated the meaning of his queſtion to be, Firſt, That his aduerſaries ſhould ſet down Names of men in all ages which they thought to be Proteſtants.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, That they ſhould ſhew out of good Authors proofe that they were Proteſtants.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, That they ſhould defend them to hold nothing contrary to the Doctrin of the Proteſtants, contained in the 39 Articles, vnto which all Engliſh Miniſters are ſworne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogers.</speaker>
                     <p>To the Second, Firſt I will ſhow the Names of ſuch as maintained our now faith in all ages, and bring good proofe.</p>
                     <p>To the Third, Firſt, It is no preiudice to our faith if the ſame Authors doe differ from vs in other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns not concerning faith, as long as they maintain our faith.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, The Church of Rome cannot produce Fathers in all ages, who doe not contradict the Councell of Trent in ſome Doctrines eſtabliſhed in the ſaid Councell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16581:9"/>
                     <speaker>Fiſher.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fiſher</hi> offered me a like proportion, to name, and proue, and defend profeſſors of Romane religion, holding nothing contrarie to the Doctrine defined in the Councell of Trent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogers.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt expreſſe whether you haue all things defined in that Councell to be matters of faith: if you doe, you can neuer performe what you haue promiſed,</p>
                     <p>I deſired you therefore <hi>M. Fiſher</hi> to expreſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ambiguitie the termes of this queſtion: whether the Proteſtant Church was viſible in all ages?</p>
                     <p>What you meane by Church? what by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants? what by viſible?</p>
                     <p>I will deliuer my opinion in defining a Proteſtant Church.</p>
                     <p>The Proteſtant Church, is a ſocietie of men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the faith expreſſed in the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, acknowledged to be ſuch in the Primitiue Church, compriſed in the Apoſtles Creede, explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the other two Creedes of Nice, &amp; Athanaſius, Miniſtring the Sacraments of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper by men of lawfull Ordination and calling.</p>
                     <p>Such a ſocietie as this was in all ages: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Proteſtant Church was in all ages.</p>
                     <p>I deſire you alſo to diſtinguiſh betweene matters of
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Diſcipline, &amp;</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, to diſtinguiſh betweene.
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Doctrine Acceſſorie. And</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Doctrin Fundamentall.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16581:9"/>Matter of faith conſiſteth not in Diſcipline, but Doctrine: and that Doctrine not acceſſorie, but fundamentall.</p>
                     <p>By this diſtinction I meane the ſame which <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> doth by <hi>Res fidei,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Per Se.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Per Accidens.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>I diſtinguiſh betweene.
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Affirmation. And</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Negation.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>In thoſe Articles of our Engliſh Church, our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is partly a trauerſing, partly a condemning of your nouelties and additions: and therefore no part of our faith; for no man would deny his owne faith; <hi>In all theſe I defend the Negatiue, and ſo it doth belong to you to proue the affirmatiue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which when you ſhall do by teſtimony of writers in all ages, I will yeeld to you.</p>
                     <p>For you prouing the affirmatiue, the negatiue will fall of it ſelfe. As for example, the firſt inſtance of negation in our Articles, is no part of the ſixt Article concerning thoſe Bookes of <hi>Eſdras, Tobie, Iudith, &amp;c:</hi> which we receiue not for Canonicall, you doe: the proofe is on your ſide.</p>
                     <p>What I require of you, I wil performe on our ſide: whatſoeuer is affirmatiue in our Articles, I will maintaine to be affirmed and taught in all ages, as the 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. Articles, the affirmatiue part of the 6. 7. 8, and ſo in the reſt, or I will yeeld vnto you: giue me inſtance with affirmation of our Articles you deny, and I will proue it in all ages: and I deſire you to ſet downe withall, which of our affirmatiue Articles you receiue: and whether we agree in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16581:10"/>
Articles of the Creede, or not.</p>
                     <p>I will do the like by you, and giue you an inſtance in your affirmatiues: ſhew me who in euery age did receiue the Bookes of <hi>Eſdras, Machabies, Tobit, Iudeth, &amp;c.</hi> for Canonicall, in the 1. 2. 3. 4 centure of yeares; this is one of the firſt points of your Tridentiue faith.</p>
                     <p>I deſire you alſo <hi>M. Fiſher,</hi> for the avoyding of confuſion to deliuer your opinion, whether all the affirmatiue Doctrines of the Councell of Trent are matters of faith <hi>Per ſe,</hi> fundamentall and neceſſarie to be held for ſaluation <hi>Fide explicata:</hi> I ſpeake <hi>de adubtis quibus facultas datur diſcendi.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And I do confeſſe that none of your ſide, or ours, haue giuen me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ull ſatisfaction in this point, which are <hi>Res fidei per ſe.</hi> I therefore propoſe this <hi>M. Fiſher</hi> as deſirous to learne, and to lay a foundation for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeding in this point of the viſible Church.</p>
                     <p>Neither will I be ſparing to deliuer my opinion with ſubmiſſion to better men, and better leaſure of my owne, (hauing bin theſe 6 moneths far from my Bookes, and farther from leaſure or repoſe to ſtudy.)</p>
                     <p>I doe not thinke that all the affirmatiue Doctrines contained in our Articles, are <hi>Res fidei per ſe,</hi> funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, neceſſarie to ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>I therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>Dogmata.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Scholae, theſe denied, worke a priuat diſsention.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Eccleſiae, theſe work an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Church.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Fidei, Theſe denied, worke an eternall damnation.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>By <hi>Eccleſiae,</hi> I meane not the eſſentiall Church, but repreſentatiue, whether generall, nationall, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16581:10"/>That it is onely an error in the latter, which is damnable, not in the firſt and ſecond, vnleſſe it be with obſtinacy.</p>
                     <p>I will giue you inſtance as well as I can, being without my Bookes.</p>
                     <p>Conſubſtantiation was a Schoole tenent <hi>Anno</hi> 1100, not a Church tenent.</p>
                     <p>Tranſubſtantiation was a Church tenent after the yeare 1200. 1. <hi>Eccleſiae Romanae,</hi> but the reall preſence, vnderſtanding thereby not a bodily preſence, but a true relation, a Sacramentall obligation, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all exhibition of his body, is <hi>Res fidei,</hi> a point of faith.</p>
                     <p>Or thus, Tranſubſtantiation was a Schoole tenent <hi>Anno</hi> 1100, a Church tenent <hi>Anno</hi> 1215, defined by <hi>Innocentius</hi> 3, <hi>in concil. Latera:</hi> but no point of faith, becauſe the bodie of religion or points of faith are without addition: As <hi>Lyrinenſis: inuitetur animarum religio rationem corporum quae &amp; quotparuilorum membra tot virorum.</hi> And as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith,</p>
                     <p>The Articles of faith do grow <hi>quoad</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Explicationem.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Non</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Quod ad ſubſtantiam.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>That which was no point of faith for the firſt 1200 yeares, could be none afterwards, <hi>vt ſupra Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lerinenſis, &amp; Aquinas.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But tranſubſtantiation was no point of faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the yeare 1200: <hi>Scotus. Ergo,</hi> tranſubſtantiation is no point of faith.</p>
                     <p>If I doe not cite the words of <hi>Scotus</hi> aright, impute it to my want of bookes, for I haue none at this time, yet I would lay the foundation of a friendly confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence without trickes, ambiguitie, or bitternes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16581:11"/>I deſire you alſo to obſerue in the citing of the Fathers, to alledge nothing for your opinion but what that Father hath held, written, and taught, <hi>apertè, frequenter, perſeueranter,</hi> or at leaſt that his words be plaine, and his opinion ſuch as that he hath not after recanted, or croſſed in his later workes.</p>
                     <p>I thinke it reaſonable alſo, that if I will iuſtifie the faith which is publikely profeſſed and receſſitated by our Church, that I produce not onely ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men deliuering their opinions, but alſo proofes of ſome Church or viſible ſocietie, who publikely profeſſed the ſame faith in all ages.</p>
                     <p>The like I expect from you.</p>
                     <p>So the firſt thing is, to expreſſe what is your faith, what is ours.</p>
                     <p>Next, what Society in all ages profeſſed, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely receſſitated with your Church or ours, doe publikely teach and receſſitate: I meane affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not negatiuely, for no man doth teach or receſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate what he doth denie.</p>
                     <p>This I haue briefely done in the definition of a Proteſtant Church.</p>
                     <p>I pray you giue me a definition of the Romane Church.</p>
                     <p>Whereas you ſay that all our Miniſters are ſworne to the 39 Articles, you are deceiued, it is not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A DIALOGVE CONCERNING THIS QVESTION, VVhere was your Church before <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Giuing good directions how to diſcouer FISHERS folly.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>VV. C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed M.DC.XXIII.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:12"/>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16581:12"/>
                  <head>Mr. W. C. his Dialogue concerning this queſtion, <hi>VVhere was your Church before Luther?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">A Dialogue betweene <hi>E</hi> and <hi>D.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ANſwer this queſtion,</hi> Where was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Euen where our doctrine was, ſometime in one coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſometime in another, as it pleaſed God in his wiſe diſpenſation, who caries the light of his Goſpell, as hee doth the Sunne through the world, to illuminate nations at ſeuerall times therewith, according to his will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That is a faire generall; but will you tell vs, who were theſe? what countrey people? what Doctors? who taught as yee teach?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Looke the Churches of <hi>Aſia, Africke</hi> and of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> conſider them as they were before the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to the height, and you ſhall ſee that they all had the ſame doctrine a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d forme of a Church that wee haue in all ſubſtantiall points pertaining to Religion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But you are not able to name one before</hi> Luther, <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all things as he did.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a peece of Sophiſtrie, whereby your decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers blind the ignorant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How ſo? ſhould not the teachers of the truth agree in all things, in one harmonie?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I grant they ſhould, and thanks be to God they do alſo in all ſubſtantiall things which are the Articles of our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16581:13"/>
faith.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Buckler of Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> publiſhed in French by M. <hi>Peter du Moulin,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh, &amp; twiſe printed, Anno 1624 is a moſt excellent book for theſe preſent times, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Luther,</hi> &amp;c. let <hi>Luther</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it at his beſt le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſure, or <hi>Sweet,</hi> or <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, of any Ieſuit or Maſſe-prieſt whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</note> But is this a good reaſon, becauſe ſome Doctors in ſome opinions differ, whereof men may be ignorant and ſaued neuertheleſſe, that therefore theſe Doctors teach no truth, and their Churches are no true Churches?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That ſeemes to be hard indeed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>You haue reaſon for you ſo to think. For in one age <hi>Victor</hi> with the Church in the Weſt was in a different opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from <hi>Policrates</hi> and the Churches of the Eaſt; and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> had his owne diſcordance with <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> and the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>athers of the primitiue Church were Chiliaſts: ſhall it thereupon follow, that becauſe in this point they taught not in all things as wee doe, that therefore they were not a Church?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is no reaſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the point of rebaptizing taught not as <hi>Cornelius:</hi> what of that? will it follow that he was not a faithfull Paſtor, or the Church of <hi>Carthage</hi> was not a true Church?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It followes not indeed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhy then do you vrge me to giue you one before <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> who in all points taught as wee teach? The Doctors of the Church both ancient and recent, are men ſubiect to infirmities; for no man vpon earth hath his vnderſtanding perfect, whereof it comes to paſſe, that in ſome things one of them differs from another: but as to the Articles of the faith and ſubſtance of Chriſtian religion whereby comes ſaluation, ſure it is <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Cyprian, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> haue all deliuered one doctrine and did teach the way of God truly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then you thinke the Fathers of the Primitiue Church were of your Religion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I thinke ſo indeed, and hope to die in the ſame faith wherein they liued and died.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It would be thought ſtrange to heare that in Italy, that the Doctors of the Primitiue Church were of the Proteſtants Religion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>No marvell though it be ſtrange there where truth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16581:13"/>
is a ſtranger: but this anſwer was giuen you and them both, by a worthy Doctor of our Church,<note place="margin">The light of Cambridge, M. Doctor <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planum.</hi>
                        </note> M. Doctor <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers,</hi> and yet we ſtand to it: <hi>Patros in maximis ſunt noſtri, in multis narij, in minimis veſtri:</hi> Such Fathers (ſaith Doctor <hi>Whitakers</hi>) as haue written before vs and you both, in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt things are ours, in many things are doubtfull, in ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt things they are yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Well, I will remember that, God willing: but in the dayes of Papiſtrie, wherewith you ſay the world was blinded, where was your Church?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Anſwer me but another queſtion, and it ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>What is that?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Doctors ſay, that when Antichriſt ſhall come, the Church ſhall flie to the Deſert, that is, as themſelues ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it.<note place="margin">The Rhemiſts vpon Reuel. 11.</note> The Church ſhall be without publike ſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and open free exerciſe of holy functions; neither ſhall it be vnknowne to the faithfull which follow it, as this day may be ſeene the like by the Church of Romane Catholikes in many parts of England.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>What doth that helpe you?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Very much. That which they themſelues ſay will be done, we ſay is done: Antichriſt hath already chaſed the Church to the wilderneſſe, and ſo oppreſſed it, that for a time it had no publike ſtate of regiment, nor open free ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of holy functions, yet was it not vnknowne to the faithfull that followed it, nor to the enemies that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed it, as this day may be ſeene by the Church of Chriſtian Catholikes in many parts of France.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Will ye make that cleare, and I thinke you haue wonne much.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat greater clearneſſe can you craue? If this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer be good to cleare the Popes Church when they ſay it will be obſcured by Antichriſt, and yet be, is it not as good to iuſtifie our Church, when we ſay, it hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by Antichriſt, and yet was?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The anſwer is good enough; only if you can, I would haue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16581:14"/>
you qualifie it more particularly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>There is not one age ſince the dayes of Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, wherein I cannot point forth men preaching and profeſſing as we doe: but becauſe your doubt is ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the time of Papiſtrie, I will let you ſee it is a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe queſtion for the Popes Church to demand of vs, where our Church then was? for they found vs alwayes in their teeth before euer <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Caluin</hi> were borne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Make that good.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">See <hi>Reinerus</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoc.</note>
                        <hi>Reinerus</hi> a popiſh Inquiſitor, who liued more then three hundred yeares ago, ſpeaking of the poore men of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and calling them in contempt <hi>Valdenſes, Leoniſtae,</hi> ſaith, they were more pernicious to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> then all other ſects,<note place="margin">3. Reaſons why the Walden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es much vexed the Rom. Church.</note> for three cauſes. Firſt, becauſe it hath been of longer continuance: for ſome ſay, this ſect hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſince the Apoſtles times. The ſecond cauſe is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more generall: for there is almoſt no Land in the which this Sect doth not creepe. The third cauſe, for that all other Sects doe bring an horror with the hainouſneſſe of their blaſphemies againſt God, but this Sect of <hi>Leoniſts</hi> hath a great ſhew of godlineſſe, becauſe they liue iuſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, and beleeue all things well concerning God, and all the Articles which are contained in the Creed, onely they blaſpheme and hate the Church of Rome.</p>
                     <p>Now there is the teſtimonie of an enemie making an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for vs, which may ſerue to ſtop the mouthes of all our enemies from demanding of vs any more, <hi>Where was your Church before</hi> Luther?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi> 1. but he calls them a Sect, and ſayes, they blaſphemed the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>So the Prieſts of the Iewes called the Church of Chriſtians <hi>a Sect of Nazarites,</hi> Acts 24.5. what is that to the matter? yet he grants they are ſuch a Sect, as firſt had been from the beginning; ſecondly, had been in all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys; and thirdly was honeſt in life and ſound in faith, ſaue onely that they held the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the Whore of <hi>Babel.</hi> And that yet this preiudice which you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16581:14"/>
haue conceiued of our Church may be further remoued out of your mind, I pray you conſider this: think you not that with good reaſon we may affirme, that we are in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them who haue taught the ſame doctrine that we teach? If our doctrine was in former ages, you will not deny that our Church was then alſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That cannot be denied.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, if you pleaſe, name me any controuerſie of religion,<note place="margin">The Ancient Fathers.</note> concerning any article of faith between vs and the Papiſts this day, and you ſhall ſee that the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers take our part in it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That is ſtrange; for they repoſe their chiefest ſtrength and truſt in the ancient Fathers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Brag what they will, it is true, I ſay, they may well boaſt in the droſſe of Fathers, and decke their errors with it, but we ſhall bring you their fineſt gold. Name you the controuerſie, and you ſhall trie that which I ſay to be a truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>There are ſo many controuerſies among you, that I know not which of them to name firſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Then will it pleaſe you to take a view of thoſe which I haue gathered for my owne priuate vſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>With a very good will: let me ſee what they are.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>They are noted &amp; ſet downe in foure ſpecial books of the Proteſtants, and I haue obſerued and collected them for my owne comfort and confirmation in the faith: for as firſt of all I learned the way of ſaluation in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſo finding that the Doctors of the primitiue Church (produced in theſe foure ſpeciall books: 1. Doctor <hi>White</hi> his <hi>Way to the true Church:</hi> 2. <hi>Illyricus</hi> his <hi>Catalogus teſtim. veritatis,</hi> augmented twice by <hi>Goularitus:</hi> 3. Doctor <hi>Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> his fiue concluſions or <hi>Theſes</hi> the fift, <hi>quinta Concluſ. quinta Theſ.</hi> in Engliſh, but more large in Latin: 4. <hi>Pola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Catholica;</hi> ſpeciall bookes, writ by foure Proteſtant Preachers) expounded the Scriptures confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the doctrine of our teachers, I was greatly therein confirmed: for theſe are the two great props of our faith,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16581:15"/>
which <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>inentius</hi> giues vs againſt all hereſies, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>You haue reaſon for you: for if your doctrine be ſo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Two maine props &amp; proofs of religion.</note> 
                        <hi>both by diuine authoritie of God in his word, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane teſtimony of the beſt Doctors of the ancient Church, they are to be iudged moſt vnworthy that make contradiction to you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe points are ſo fully performed (as I haue ſaid) in three ſpecial books by three worthy Proteſtant Diuines, and ſo methodically ſet downe, that I thinke my ſhewing to you of theſe three bookes, and your reading of them will moſt fully content and ſatisfie you; I ſay againe, by Gods help<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they will giue you moſt full ſatisfaction, as alſo to all others who with indifferencie wil vouchſafe to reade them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I pray you who be thoſe three Diuines who haue writ thoſe three bookes, and which be the bookes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Doctor <hi>White</hi> is the firſt, and the booke is, his <hi>Way to the true Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cus Illyricus</hi> his <hi>Catalogus teſtium veritatis,</hi> aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented twice by <hi>Simon Goulartius,</hi> ſet out by him the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time in one volume in a large Folio.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Doctor <hi>Reinolds</hi> his ſix Concluſions in Engliſh, placed at the end of his Conference with <hi>Hart:</hi> but it is his fift Concluſion which I meane for this purpoſe, <hi>quinta Concluſ.</hi> or his ſix <hi>Theſes</hi> in Latin. of his laſt augmented Edition, and thereof I meane his fift <hi>Theſ. quinta Theſ.</hi> more full then the Engliſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And what haue theſe foure Diuines performed in thoſe foure bookes, to giue comfort, content and ſatisfaction on this very point we haue now in hand, viz.</hi> Where your Church, doctrine, teachers were before Luther? <hi>for I aſſure you, this is the maine matter, which troubleth many at this preſent: for</hi> Campian <hi>was not ſo buſie in Queen</hi> Elizabeths <hi>dayes with his</hi> Audito nomine Eccleſiae, hoſtis expalluit; <hi>but</hi> Fiſher, Sweet, Clarke <hi>and other Ieſuites are as buſie now in King</hi> Iames <hi>his dayes, euen at this preſent, with their</hi> Where was your Church
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16581:15"/>
before <hi>Luther?</hi> Where your Preachers? where your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors? where your doctrine? let vs heare their names; Names, names, names, names, <hi>cries the</hi> Fiſher <hi>catched in his owne Net.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What haue they performed? enough at the full (in the mercie of God) to ſatisfie you and all other indifferent Readers, that without preiudice looke into thoſe their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How might I come by thoſe bookes? may I meet with them in Pauls Church-yard for I would very gladly buy them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>You may moſt eaſily: but ſtay, let mee a little call back that word, for they are ſo faſt bought vp, that I doubt they are almoſt out of print, for (and that worthily) they are exceedingly in requeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>So much the more the Printers are too blame, that they giue not a ſecond impreſſion to them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſecond impreſſion, ſay you; why Doctor <hi>Whites Way to the true Church</hi> hath beene printed foure ſeuerall times, now within a few yeares, and notwithſtanding are almoſt all ſold vp, but I heare a fifth impreſſion is now in hand. <hi>Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia, Illyricus</hi> and Doctor <hi>Reinolds,</hi> their bookes (before named) haue beene diuers times im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed alſo; ſo that you need not blame the Printers, who are carefull to make new impreſſions, and new ſupplies of bookes ſo worthy, and ſo much in requeſt, and ſo greatly ſought after.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This ſhould argue, that their bookes (by Gods bleſſing) are very powerfull, and win many to the truth, they vent ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly faſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>O yes, God be thanked, preaching and writing ſucceed happily with a bleſſed ſucceſſe: doubt you not but at this day for one Papiſt, England doth enioy xx. xl. yea rather an hundred Proteſtants. Maſſes and ſtage-playes grow odious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>You make me long for theſe foure bookes, I would gladly be in hand with them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Sir, ſeeing your longing is ſo great, I haue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16581:16"/>
them at hand for you, vſe them ſo long as you pleaſe: now I fetch them out of my Studie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Are theſe they, Sir, I pray you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes indeed, theſe are the very bookes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now I pray you Sir, before that we open them, tell me in briefe what they ſay and performe in theſe matters.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>That, good Sir, I will moſt willingly performe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And I moſt willingly liſten and giue attentiue care vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>God direct with his holy Spirit, and giue a bleſſing in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus. Theſe foure bookes following do fully furniſh any Scholler to make anſwer to all Ieſuits, Maſſe-prieſts, <hi>Fiſher, Clarke, Sweet,</hi> &amp;c. to that queſtion, <hi>Where was your Religion before the dayes of</hi> Luther?</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Doctor <hi>White</hi> (to begin firſt with him) in his book intituled <hi>The Way to the true Church,</hi> Digreſſion 52. ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the preſent Religion of the Romane Church was obſerued and reſiſted in all ages as it came in and increaſed; naming withall the perſons that made reſiſtance, and the points wherein, and the time when, from fiftie yeares to fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, throughout all ages ſince Chriſt, compendiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued out of hiſtory, for the ſatisfying of their error, that ſo much conceit the antiquitie of Papiſtrie, and thinke it was neuer controlled till <hi>Luthers</hi> time. And Digreſſion 48 Sect. 50. the ſaid Doctor <hi>White</hi> ſetteth downe a briefe and direct anſwer to the Papiſts, when they ſay, we cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne a viſible company profeſſing the ſame faith in euery point that we doe, euer ſince Chriſt till now, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Flacius Illyricus</hi> (the ſecond I named) in his booke intituled <hi>Catalogus teſtim veritatis,</hi> A Catalogue of the witneſſes of the truth, augmented twice by <hi>Simon Goular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and by him the ſecond time ſet out in one volume, in a large Folio, ſheweth, that the preſent rel gion of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> obſerued and reſiſted in all ages as it came in and increaſed; naming withall the perſons that made the reſiſtance, and the points wherein, and the time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16581:16"/>
when, from an hundred yeares to an hundred, throughout all ages ſince Chriſt, compendiouſly obſerued out of hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, for the ſatisfying of their error, that ſo much conceit the antiquitie of Papiſtrie, and thinke it was neuer control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led till <hi>Luthers</hi> time.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The third is Doctor <hi>Reinolds</hi> (that light of Oxford) in his fift Concluſion, <hi>quinta Concluſ.</hi> in Engliſh, ioyned to the end of his Conference with <hi>Hart;</hi> but far more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lly in his fift Latin Theſis, <hi>quinta Theſ.</hi> of the laſt augmented Edition, ſheweth that the preſent Church of Rome is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the holy Catholicke Church, nor a ſound member of the Catholicke Church; that the preſent Religion of the Romane Church was obſerued and reſiſted in all ages; bringeth in abundantly proofes and teſtimonies out of the ancient Fathers, Councels and records, good Authors, School-men, the Papiſts owne writings, &amp;c. in all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerted points betwixt the Proteſtants and Papiſts.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The fourth is <hi>Amandus Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica,</hi> though named the laſt, yet as admirable as the reſt, yea in one thing more admirable, viz. in bringing in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers in all the controuerted points betwixt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts in all ages moſt fully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>You come to the point indeed, and ſay more then euer I heard; and I hope theſe your foure bookes wil make all this good that you haue named.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>They will indeed moſt plentifully: take them away with you, and keepe them euen ſo long as you pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>E.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I thanke you moſt heartily, good Sir; you bring me to a feaſt indeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> what varietie of daintie diſhes haue you ſet before me?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>God in Chriſt Ieſus bleſſe them vnto you.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16581:17"/>
                  <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Catholica,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robert Cooke</hi> his booke concerning <hi>counterfet Fathers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Catholica</hi> is written in common-place manner, out of the ancient Fathers and other good Authors, from the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to the times of <hi>Luther,</hi> handling the principall controuerted points methodically betwixt the Proteſtants and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, written purpoſely to ſatisfie that demand of Papiſts, <hi>Where was the Proteſtants religion before the times of</hi> Luther? Oh that ſome good religious Scholler or other would tranſlate it into Engliſh, for the common profite of the Church of England, againſt the inſulting brags of <hi>Fiſher</hi> and other Papiſts, who ſay, we had no religion before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> times, that hee hatched it, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh likewiſe that M. <hi>Robert Cooke</hi> his Latin Treatiſe concerning <hi>counterfet Fathers</hi> was tranſlated into Engliſh, for the good of thoſe who vnderſtand not Latin; Papiſts alledging counterfet Fathers ſo often.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:17"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16581:18"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
